The thing that happens is if you have
one subscription tier at one price,
there's two buckets of users that don't
get their needs met. There are users who
just can't afford the price if it's $30
a month or they don't want to pay the
price. And then the other thing that
people don't think about enough is that
there's a whole bunch of people that are
willing to pay $50 or $60. So, you're
leaving money on the table on both sides
of that subscription. Hello, I'm your
host David Bernard and with me today,
Revenue Cat CEO Jacob ID. Our guest
today is Robbie Meta, former chief
product officer at Tinder, now working
with high growth consumer and AI
startups as a hands-on product adviser.
On the podcast, we talk with Robbie
about subscriptions as a force
multiplier for consumables, why
narratives matter more than metrics in
goal setting, and why you might want to
try a longer onboarding or a shorter
one. Hey Robbie, thanks so much for
joining us on the podcast today.
>> Yeah, thanks so much for having me. I'm
excited to be here. and Jacob. Always
nice to have you as well.
>> I'm back. I'm here. It snowed three
inches today, David, on November 8th or
whatever day it is. It's crazy. It's
obsessing.
>> Nice. I'm in Texas and it almost froze
last night. So, you were out in San
Francisco, Robbie. So, you don't have
any
>> I'm actually in LA. It was 80 degrees a
few days ago. Yeah. Wow.
>> Sorry. What a country. What a
>> It was It was 80 degrees yesterday and
then it got dropped. So, anyhow, on to
subscription apps. So, I wanted to kick
things off with this chart you created
from your experience at Tinder, and I
I've talked about this chart so much. I'
I've called it your famous chart because
I've just obsessed over this chart ever
since I first saw it. And it's always
hard to talk about charts on a podcast.
So, for the video podcast, we'll we'll
see if the production team can actually
overlay this chart. But for those
listening along, you might want to just
pause and go to the show notes and link
to this chart because I I think the
having the visual in your head is is
actually going to be super helpful to
kind of understand what we're talking
about here. Uh so on the x- axis is
number of paying users. On the y ais is
willingness to pay. And the idea is you
want to fit this demand curve. So the
what Tinder did so beautifully is that
with the Tinder Plus product, it was a
lower price product. So you had a lower
willingness to pay, but you had way more
users uh who are willing to pay that
amount. Then for Tinder Gold, you have a
higher willingness to pay, higher price
product, but then it's fewer users who
are willing to pay. And then Tinder
Platinum has the highest willingness to
pay the highest price point uh but the
fewest number of users. But the
beautiful thing is this creates a nice
stairst step where you meet people where
they are on the demand curve. You know
how much they're willing to spend. And
then the thing about Tinder and what
Tinder did so well is that you also
layer consumables on top of that. So the
super likes and other consumables fit
that demand curve even better because on
top of each of these subscription tiers,
you can actually spend more money. So
I've described the chart, but tell me
about why you created the chart and how
you thought about this at Tinder to even
create the chart and and the the
conversations that led to this even
becoming Tinder's monetization
philosophy that then became the chart.
>> Yeah, definitely. So the idea behind the
chart is it's very similar to a lot of
the charts in like economics 101 where
you have a demand curve and then you're
just trying to figure out how to price
things and as price goes up demand goes
down. So that's the theoretical model.
The thing that happens very concretely
in practice is if you have one
subscription tier at one price, we know
there's two buckets of users that don't
get their needs met. There are users who
just can't afford the price. If it's $30
a month or they don't want to pay the
price, there's a whole bunch of users
who might have some willingness to pay
that you're actually not going to
capture because they are they're not
willing to go to $30. You know, maybe
they'd be willing to spend $10 or $20,
but you're just not going to get them as
customers. And then the other thing that
people don't think about enough is that
yeah, you have a bunch of people who are
willing to pay $30. within those people,
there's a whole bunch of people that are
willing to pay $50 or $60 to leaving
money on the table on both sides of that
subscription. And so what you can do is
you can add additional subscription
tiers, maybe a lower price subscription
or a higher price subscription. And then
you can partially address the problem,
but you still have this open space. You
still have, you know, in between the
subscriptions there's these cracks of
people that have a higher willingness to
pay or a lower willingness to pay whose
needs aren't met. And that's where alle
cart purchases come in. And so in
addition to having, you know, you can
have maybe two or three subscription
tiers going beyond that is going to be
too complicated. You can also have
microtransactions. So people depending
on what they need, can purchase as much
or as little as they want. And that
allows you to get to a much more perfect
price discrimination. And so this
combination of a subscription set of
tiers as well as microtransaction
products turns out to be one of the most
optimal ways especially within consumer
to price your your product. It works
really well in dating. Tinder's really
proven that. It also works incredibly
well in gaming and we've seen now a lot
of game companies have moved to this
idea of having a subscription as well as
having all of these things that you can
purchase within the game. Do you think
the the benefit of having the
subscription is just like it sort of
recurringly fills like half of that
demand curve area, right? Because like
in theory, if you didn't have those sort
of commit recurring commitments, you
could fill that all with consumables,
right? If the if that's truly where the
demand curve is, do you think it just
like generally raises, you know, the
spending under the curve or what's the
interplay there? Yeah, I think it's just
a good like a single subscription is
just a really good threshold
monetization point where there are a
whole bunch of users who are willing to
pay that amount. And so by setting, you
know, by framing the price there, by
getting people to think about the value
in that way, you can move a significant
set of free users over to the paid side
in a way that is very predictable. You
know, that's another thing from a
company standpoint. subscriptions are
really nice in terms of the
predictability of the revenue. The
challenge with having a microtransaction
only approach which theoretically should
actually be perfect price discrimination
because you know people will buy as much
as they want. Um but in reality like the
psychology of it is you know if people
have a need one month they'll spend
more. If they have less of a need they
spend less and then that leads to this
kind of up and down for you as a
business that you need to manage
through. And so subscription is a nice
way to kind of ratchet that up and say,
"Okay, there's this kind of flat rate
that we want to get people into. It's
good for them because they're getting a
ton of value each month. It's good for
us because it makes our business more
predictable." And then you can use
additional tiers or additional
microtransaction purchases to kind of
fill in the business model from there.
>> Does Tinder have a free tier? I haven't
I haven't used it enough personally as a
happily married man. Uh, and how do you
think about the free tier in relation to
this? Yeah, actually that was one of
Tinder's innovations. So dating in the
very early days with match and e-harmony
was paid only. In order to be a member
of the site, in order to match with
people, you had to be a paid member. And
there were a couple of companies that
innovated around freetoplay dating. The
first is OkayCid and the second is
Plenty of Fish. Both of them saw really
fast user growth because essentially
they pull down any friction. they get a
much larger number of people into the
product. And that's always great when
you have a product that has network
effects. You want as many people using
it as possible. Tinder came in and said,
"Okay, we're going to do the same thing.
We're going to have a free-to-play
product about, you know, kind of 85 to
90% of users are entirely free. Um, so
there's very little friction to get
started. There's lots of people that are
on Tinder that are swiping on each
other, that are messaging with each
other. So, it's a really vibrant
ecosystem from that standpoint. And for
a subset of those users, kind of 10 to
15% who want to get more out of this
experience, who want to be able to match
with more people, who want to be able to
match with less effort, they're willing
to pay. Um, and that's where the
subscription tiers and the
microtransactions come into place. And
that's I think one of the most
interesting questions for consumer app
builders right now is do you want to
have a free tier, do you want to have a
limited pay trial, or do you want to not
have any trial at all? Do you just want
to have people come straight in and pay
right away? And depending on what your
product is doing for people and the
psychology associated with that and the
network effects associated with that,
the right answer for one company may be
totally different than the right answer
for another company.
>> Doesn't work without a lot of people,
right? So you don't want to like gate
it's actually interesting to me that the
the and I'm sure there's there's
probably reasons this works, but like so
many dating apps were fully paid on both
sides of the it seems like it would
really limit your network effects,
right? Um be able to get like you know
maybe it works in big cities, but
anywhere outside of that would be really
tough. you'd have just like tough uh
meeting supply and demand I would think.
>> Totally. And there's an interesting
thing there where Tinder needs as many
people as possible and then there's, you
know, broadly there's two categories of
people. There's people that are getting
a lot of swipe rights and there's people
that are not getting a lot of swipe
rights. That tends to break down on
gender lines. So women get a lot more
people swiping on them than men do. And
because you have these two different
characteristics of people within the
system, it's important to be free so
that the people who are, you know, in
demand, the people that others want to
swipe right on are incentivized to come
into the product and don't have to have
to pay to be there.
>> For payers, it's predominantly men. On
Tinder,
>> it is predominantly men. It's a little
bit more balanced on Hinge and a little
bit more balanced on Bumble. But the
needs of someone who's getting a lot of
people swiping right on them and the
needs of someone who's not getting as
many people swiping right on them are
very different. And the Tinder paid
products tend to focus on people that
are not getting a lot of swipes. So
they're things like boosts and super
likes which help you get more matches.
Whereas Bumble, for example, has
products for people that are getting a
lot of inbound attention to help them
kind of filter and sort. I was going to
ask if Tinder ever considered like
bifurcating their products like for the
which side of the supply demand curve
you're on. Right.
>> Yeah. I think there's an interesting and
really significant opportunity there.
Tinder hasn't really been able to land
it yet. Bumble, I think, has landed it
much better because they've been um
they've been focused on the female user
ever since inception. That's part of
their brand. And I think Hinge has done
a really nice job of saying, "Hey, we're
focused on people that are here, you
know, for serious relationships across
genders." And they have a more, I think,
broad set of products.
>> It's like hiring market tools, right?
There's like all these tools out there
to help you apply to jobs and then
there's on the other side there's all
these SASes to help you filter out the
like y
>> there's money to be made at every on
every side of the market.
to Jacob's point earlier about um not
having the subscription u and and I I
should have known Tinder had a free
tier, but do those free users then spend
on consumables and and is that a
significant part of monetization is
having those free users spend on
consumables and then do you monetize
them any other ways like ads? I don't
know if this is on purpose or not, but
interestingly, there is a there's a
little chunk on the the value demand
curve here where right of the cheapest
subscription, there is actually no AP or
no no consumables.
>> So, I didn't do that deliberately, but
it is the case that very few free users
actually buy microtransactions. It tends
to be that these subscriptions are kind
of force multipliers for the micro
transactions
>> because like obviously there's probably
10 times as many or nine times as many
free users as there are subscription.
But it'd be interesting to see if they
still don't generate a like um
meaningful amount of volume.
>> I think part of it is a product value
problem. So the the two main
microtransactions that you can buy are
super likes and boosts. Both of which
help you get more matches. And then the
main thing you get from Tinder Gold is
you can see who swiped right on you. So
the two products work together. You can
get more people to swipe right on you
and then you can see who's swiping right
on you and those work together to get
you more more matches. And so if you
don't have Tinder Gold, the value of
those microtransaction products is a lot
less.
>> I would also imagine too if your like
entry level subscription product price
point is pretty low, there's probably
not a whole lot of people to the right
of that. You know what I mean? That are
that are like, "Oh, it's, you know,
$4.99 a month's too much. I got to pay a
dollar a month or whatever." like
there's probably not a ton of volume
there.
>> 100%. And then that that cheaper tier is
meant to be an on-ramp. Like find people
that are willing to jump the penny gap,
get them into a paid product that shows
them that they can get a lot more from
the experience and then from there you
can upgrade them to Tinder Gold or to
the microtransaction products.
>> And do you show ads to the free users?
Are they otherwise monetized?
>> They are. There is um there are ads. Uh
it's a small part of Tinder's revenue.
It's just the the numbers in terms of
like, you know, the value of an ad
impression versus the value of someone
subscribing to Tinder is such a huge
difference in terms of order of
magnitude. It's a nice way to fill in
the gap, but it's not like a main
business driver.
>> It's incremental. Everybody I've talked
to ads is like less than a quarter. You
know, I'm sure there are exceptions to
that, but it's it's not a huge part of
the revenue mix from everybody I've
talked to, but it's meaningful. I mean
10 20 15% you know part of your revenue
mix is you should do it but like it's
not going to be the the workhorse for
your business in most cases
>> for sure and it helps you subsidize the
free users.
>> This happened after your time but what
are your thoughts on the super premium
tier that Tinder was experimenting with
and have you heard anything about how
it's performed? So I actually started
work on Tinder Platinum and this came
out of it sort of came out of insights
from this graphic knowing that there
were people on Tinder Gold who were
purchasing a lot of microtransactions.
People spending a hundred to $250 a
month on Tinder. And what we wanted to
understand is why are they spending this
amount? What's their motivation? What
are the things that we could do from a
product standpoint to create something
that better meets their needs? And that
was the genesis of Tinder Platinum. And
it really came down to the core value of
Tinder, which is one of the questions
was, is this people signaling? Like, are
they trying to signal wealth or
something like that by spending a lot on
Tinder or is it more utilitarian? Do
people just want to match with more
folks? And it turns out it was more
utilitarian, like people are just
looking for more matches. And so, Tinder
Platinum, you gives people access to
additional super likes and additional
boost. So, it bundles that together. You
know, one of the interesting things
about the monetization products within
Tinder, and I think this applies
elsewhere, is Tinder is a game that
operates by a certain set of rules.
Like, if I swipe right on you, you can't
necessarily see that I did that unless
you have Tinder Gold. And then you can
break the rule because you've paid and
you can now have access to that feature.
The other rule that was sort of golden
in Tinder is you can't message someone
until you've matched. One of the
products that's in Tinder Platinum is
the ability to message someone before
you've before you've matched, which is
incredibly valuable for folks to be able
to get more matches.
>> LinkedIn has that feature, too.
>> It's remarkably similar in certain ways.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. But no, I was talking about the
the $500 a month uh one that they had
been experimenting with the the Uber
Uber platinum. I don't even know what
they call it.
>> Yeah. I'm not even familiar with that.
Yeah. So definitely after my time
>> the number of people but you still
should keep finding area under the curve
potentially because I was like what what
would be the hyper premium version of
like it'd be a personal matchmaker or
something like this right like would you
go all the way that far I think like at
some point you go beyond what is the uh
in the practical scope of like a
software company right to do what you do
but but this is off in the the rails but
like Airbnb's done this like more as a
marketing thing you know there's like
crazy experiences like there's no way
that makes money for them I guess but
they have they have I I've heard Brian
talk about this several times which is
like the hundred star experience right
and they've you've seen them kind of put
it into their product um you know but I
think like what we're talking about here
is like how you go from like selling
something for the one star two star
three star four star right like that's
probably 80% of the value you're going
to capture is is within you know it's
matching to that that that sort of
spectrum
>> I think so and then there's like there's
always the whales who are willing to
spend more and so it's good to cater to
them games do a really good job with
that and I think there's also So the
brand signaling if you can have really
premium products within your brand or
within your product ecosystem that
suggests that it's you know it's a
premium place to be.
>> We're we're actually talking about this
at AppGrowth annual and it and to your
point Jacob it is kind of beyond the
typical playbook of a high gross margin
software play but for a lot of apps
there are potential to do small things
that aren't sc that don't scale for the
people who are just willing to spend
more or want those kind of different
experiences. So at app growth annual I
was talking to a guy who has a
meditation app and was struggling to
grow and started offering classes and
intensives and week-long things and he I
think he followed up recently with me
and said he's now almost doubled
revenue. So the the digital product is
providing half the revenue now and these
in-person experiences, Zoom calls and
other things are providing the other
half. And so when you have this base of
users and again you know for Tinder at
the scale of Tinder maybe it doesn't
make sense but this is oneonone matching
for 10k matchmaker maybe
>> those high gross margins right when
you're at Tinder scale but when you're
at a smaller scale it's it's potentially
worth considering here. Yeah it's
>> interesting. H how did y'all go about um
staging into this three tier model and
layering those on top? And was was there
worry about confusion and um you know I
know you're the app is really careful to
not show a payw wall with like all three
options at the same time but what what
was the thinking as you started to work
toward fitting this demand curve? It was
pretty organic. So like I wish I could
say you know we had this graphic and
like you know the company sort of
lattered into this strategy very
intentionally. I think it was more of an
organic process of launching one
subscription seeing how it does figuring
out what are the things that people
really value in that bundle. What are
the things that are less important?
What's the next level that you can
provide someone? And so for a very long
time it was basically just Tinder P
Tinder Plus plus Tinder Gold. And then
Tinder Platinum came after looking and
saying actually there there are people
that are spending a lot. How can we
better meet meet their needs? And
actually there was one of the
interesting things behind platinum was
people would spend more if they could
get more utility. We weren't hitting the
the limit of what they were they wanted
to spend. They were hitting the limit of
what Tinder could do for them. Um and so
you know coming up with a product that
met their needs was important. And then
for the microtransactions, it was
largely about like how can we create
things that enable people to match more
effectively. Um, boost is similar to,
you know, the boost on LinkedIn where
your profile gets seen more by people in
the ecosystem. Superike is the ability
to send someone a like that's
differentiated. And so when you send
someone a super like versus a regular
like, they're three times more likely to
match with you. And then there were a
bunch of other microtransaction products
that Tinder has tried along the way.
Some of which have stuck, some of which
which haven't. So it's a really organic,
very experimental process. I think one
of the interesting things about Tinder,
I don't know if this is still the case,
but it used to be that Tinder had more
skews in the Apple App Store than any
other app because Tinder would test out
$7.99, $8.99, $9.99 for Tinder, Tinder
Plus, and then, you know, other price
points for Tinder Gold and then other
price points for boosts and then bundles
of of boosts and super likes. And so
there were literally hundreds and
hundreds of different SKs available
because of all the testing. And then all
that testing would get multiplied by
different locations. And so if you're
in, you know, the pricing is going to be
different in the UK versus in South
America versus in the US. So it's all
pretty experimental and organic. I think
a really key thing that the company did
well though is understanding the
underlying user behavior of what are
people looking for from the product and
then creating products that really map
to that user behavior and help people
get value um get more matches for less
time spent. this being kind of the
plutonic ideal of monetization. I know a
lot of people would love to get to this,
but having advised a lot of startups
since your time there, I'd imagine
you've started to build some kind of
ideas around the game theory of like
what kind of products this works for and
what kind of products it doesn't. Uh any
thoughts there? One of them is like that
core question of are you free to play?
Do you have a limited free trial or are
you paid only? I think that's the first
question to ask. And freeto play works
if you have really significant network
effects. You know, a limited paid trial
works if you can get the person into a
habit loop really fast. You've got seven
days to get them into that loop of using
your product and you want to limit the
friction to actually for them to get in
and then get that habit loop built. That
works. If on the other hand, you need
someone to be financially committed in
order to really adopt your product. I
think an interesting example here are
gyms, right? You would never want to do
a 7-day free trial at a gym. Instead,
you want to charge people upfront and
now they have both a financial
commitment and as well as a personal
commitment to go and to use the gym. And
so, I think that's the first question to
answer. And then once you've answered
that, then you can figure out, okay,
where do we start in terms of a
subscription? and what's the right price
point for the first tier and then for
microtransaction products I think it's
important to understand how does the
value that someone get scale with their
usage when they get a lot of value from
their product what are they doing more
of in order to get that value and then
you can create microtransaction products
that really meet that that need and so
you know the best allocart or
microtransaction products do have that
scaling effect of you know 10 is going
to be 10 times better than, you know,
one. 100 is going to be 10 times better
than 10. As long as they're scaling
linearly or about that, then people want
to buy more of it as they're getting
more value. But then you also got to
figure out like what those users would
actually be willing to pay those 10
times or more for. And that doesn't kind
of break the game. You know, if you're a
scanner app and you limit it to 10 scans
a month and then you pay a dollar per
additional scan, I mean, that's just not
gonna probably fly, you know. So, for
certain kind of utility apps and other
things, there's maybe not that kind of
similar game theory approach where
people would be willing to pay
additional consumables for those kind of
products and experiences, right?
>> Yeah. I think it it depends.
So, one of the things I think people
undervalue is just the fact that someone
is using your product. The fact that
they've installed the app or they've
gone to your website, they're using it,
they're there means that, you know,
people have a lot of stuff to do other
than use your product. The fact that
they're doing it means they're pretty
highly motivated. And so, that means
that they have an interesting level of
willingness to pay. And so I think it's
better to start out with something
that's a little bit higher, especially
going back to that threshold thing that
we were talking about before, like get
people into a subscription that's $20 a
month or $30 a month, whatever the
framing is for your particular space,
and then you can kind of optimize from
there. I think a lot of companies and
founders make the mistake of
undermonetizing their users and then
they build a system where like, okay,
you can get your first thing for a
dollar and then you can get five more of
them for $3. And now you're in a system
where a user has to be incredibly
engaged in your app in order for you to
be making a reasonable arpoo on a
monthly basis. So set that high water
line of 20 bucks or 30 bucks. You've got
a really good place to start. If
nobody's willing to do that, then you've
got a product market fit problem,
especially if there's already framing
for that price in the market. And then
that suggests that you should be working
on product market fit, not monetization.
And if they are willing to do that, then
you can optimize from there.
>> And you mentioned, you know, a lot of
founders are undermonetized. any any
specific examples come to mind where you
think if if you could go in and apply
this playbook to their business, you
would, you know, two or 3x their revenue
because they're they're just currently
quite undermonetized.
>> Yeah, I think Granola is a good example.
So, I use Whisper Flow and Granola every
day incessantly. Whisper Flow had a
limited paid trial. They got me into
that habit loop. I started using it and
then once the, you know, once it came
time to pay, it wasn't even a thought. I
was like, I have to I'm using this every
day. I need to keep using this. versus
Granola, they have some sort of free
tier, which I don't fully understand
what the limits are, but I've never paid
for the product even though I use it
every day,
>> you know. And as we were talking, it
came to mind. Riverside is a great
example of this. I I think we're only
paying like hundred or $200 a month for
Riverside, but it's so incredibly
valuable to what we do with the podcast.
It is such a drop in the bucket compared
to my time. The production team, you
know, we send mics to guests. I mean,
that's a hundred bucks a pop. we're
paying them, you know, less than we
spend in microphones to send to guests.
Um, so there, you know, that's an
example of of probably being way
undermonetized, but it's it's hard to
differentiate and find the those
features that I would be willing to pay
for that the, you know, hobbyist
podcaster wouldn't pay for and then
delineating all the different ways to to
charge for that. I mean that's an
interesting thing with the going back to
the Tinder examples just like the um
because you know at some point Riverside
is a counterpoint if somebody's doing
like a for fun side podcast whatever
$100 a month is probably a big ask what
we're doing obviously it's not a not
even meaningful um but for Tinder Tinder
is an app that actually you know the the
success case of Tinder is worth a lot of
money right like you know not directly
necessary but it is it's like to to find
a soulmate or even just like
companionship or whatever or a good time
like that's actually quite valuable. So,
you can charge quite a bit to lever on
to that, right? Go back to David Scanner
app. It's like, well, I mean, I either
scan the scan the document or I don't
like this is there's not a huge like
your product market fit problem there.
It's just that like that's just not a
just not a compelling there's not a lot
of value uh there. But, you know, I
founders I think often, especially early
stage, like so undervalue their
products, unless maybe they're a second
time founder or they're doing some very
specific like price arbitrage thing.
Like maybe that's what Granola is doing.
I I don't know anything about Granola,
but maybe they're just like, "Hey,
>> we've got we got a bunch of venture
money. We're just going to like dig a
giant hole and it's fine because then
we're going to be on every app and we'll
figure it out later." But I I've seen
less of that and more of the like, you
know, oh, I don't think it's worth that
much. Oh, I don't feel like the product
is ready. da da da da da. But to your
point, like if you don't price it in the
market at a competitive rate, you're not
going to know your best way to measure
product market fit. Like you can measure
it with surveys and all that other
stuff, but there's nothing more
revealing than if somebody's going to
like open their wallet, you know, and
pay you, I feel like, is the best way to
measure product market fit. 100%. I
think that that framing thing is really
important. You know, the fact that you
guys are sending out microphones, that's
a hundred bucks a guest, right? And
you're willing to do that. The analog in
Tinder is we thought, you know, a
hundred to $200 a month, that's a
massive amount to be spending on Tinder
a month. Why are people spending that
much? And we talked to people and they
said, look, if I'm going out on a couple
of dates a month, that's like 400 bucks.
And so, actually, you know, spending
$100 on Tinder is actually a really good
investment for me relative to the amount
that I'm spending on this need, which is
I want to date people. I want to meet
people. And so, you know, if you have a
product that is solving an important
need for someone, there's a system
around that that kind of fits into the
problem that you're solving. And so, you
should think about what the value is of
that system rather than just like, you
know, oh, 20 bucks a month is a really
good place to start because that's what
everyone else is charging.
>> Yeah. And I brought up scanner apps as
this canonical example of it's free. You
can do it in the notes app. And this
actually goes to your point exactly that
the scanner there's scanner apps making
really great money. Why are they making
really good money? because they layer on
the products that are valuable to
people. If you're scanning on a daily
basis and that scan needs to go into a
certain workflow, like a lot of the
scanner apps that are succeeding, it's
because they have inbuilt storage. They
have OCR when OCR, you know, they added
OCR when OCR wasn't a thing and that's
what people were willing to pay for. the
cloud storage, the easy sharing, the
workflows, like they layer onto what
would otherwise be this commodity
transaction, the things that are
actually valuable to people and that's
how they make their money and how they
find that product market fit. To Jacob's
point, is like they add the value and
people pay for it.
>> Yeah, 100%. And you know, if you're
getting 200, 300 pieces of paper a month
for your business and you need to be
able to scan it really easily, you know,
that fits within the broader context of
your business. Adobe Acrobat Reader
Edit, which is like their big scanner
app on iOS, $6.3 million a month.
Congratulations, Adobe. That's amazing.
Yeah,
>> it's almost a hundred million dollar run
rate on a scanner.
>> Well, I I wanted to move on and talk
about this company you were working with
this year, uh, Sesame Care, who moved
from a three-step checkout to a 25step
checkout and boosted conversion 40%. So,
I kind of stole the thunder there. Why
did that happen?
So Sesame is a really interesting
company. It's creating an alternative to
the typical health healthcare market
within the US. So the healthcare market
in the US is completely intermediated by
health insurance. You know, in order to
go see a doctor, you typically will give
them your health insurance and then you
might have copay or not have a copay.
It's a system as we can see what's
happening with the government right now
that is in many ways broken. And the
model with Sesame is let's actually just
create a free direct marketplace between
doctors and patients. Doctors can choose
how much they want to charge. Patients
can pay that in cash if they need to.
And that makes sense for a lot of people
who are both uninsured, but increasingly
there's people who are underinsured,
where you can actually see a doctor for
less than what your co-pay would be. One
of the really key cash pay kind of areas
within healthcare over the last two or
three years has been weight loss
medication. There's been, you know, with
Ompic and WGO and Zepbound, there are
these new medications that people want
access to that their doctor may or may
not want to prescribe that, you know,
they may or may not want to pay cash for
for the medicines themselves. And so, a
number of companies have launched direct
to patient services around weight loss.
Sesame, we initially launched a program
with Costco where you could come in uh
you get low price on having access to
care and then seeing if weight loss
medication is right for you. Um, we had
a ve, you know, a very typical checkout
there. It was three screens. You kind of
get in, you check out. And then we
launched a much more sophisticated
version of the program as sort of like a
V2. Um, where we expanded the intake
from, you know, basically just a little
bit of information to a checkout screen.
Instead, we now have uh 20 different
questions. We estimate the amount of
weight that you could lose on the
medication. We get your medical history.
We ask why you're looking to lose
weight. What other things you've tried?
And so it's just a really comprehensive
intake. And we saw a higher conversion
rate because as part of that intake,
people got increasing confidence that
the care that they were going to get is
really good, really comprehensive. We
weren't just focusing on just being a
kind of pill mill sort of approach. And
so by the time that you got to the
checkout screen, people were much more
likely to check out. And the
step-to-step conversion rate that we
were seeing from one question to the
next is north of 99%. And so it's a
really good example of how sometimes the
best way to optimize your intake or your
onboarding is not to simplify it, but to
extend it around the psychology of the
user so that you're giving them the
information and the motivation that they
need in order to feel really good about
completing that process.
>> But Tinder famously had a super fast
less than a minute of onboarding. What's
the spectrum there? How do you think
about the
uber simple onboarding and where that
actually works and should continue to be
applied? Because I think there's a lot
of apps where that probably should still
be the case and you're going to, you
know, squash your conversion by
introducing 25 steps between getting
into the app and actually achieving some
kind of goal. like how do you think
about that spectrum from a you know
super frictionless onboarding as quick
as possible to intentionally adding
friction?
>> Yeah, it's a really good question. I
think it comes down to what is the aha
moment for your product? What's the
moment where you're delivering a
significant amount of value in the case
of weight loss? The the value moment is
when a person meets face to face with
their doctor. And it's much better for
their doctor to come in knowing all of
the information that you entered about
yourself and be able to use the time
that you have with the doctor to talk
about the questions that you have to see
whether or not the weight loss
medication is good for you to get you
the information that you need to make
sure you can get it covered by insurance
or whatever it else it is. And so moving
the information gathering out of that
visit and into the intake phase one gets
people excited about the fact that this
is a really comprehensive program and
then makes the most use out of that aha
moment where it's a patient talking to a
doctor and that creates the value. And
so the shorter intake actually meant
that the doctor was having to ask a lot
of those same questions in the visit and
burn up valuable time where the patients
questions weren't getting answered. But
what's the aha moment for dating? The
aha moment for dating is getting into a
conversation with someone. And if you
could shorten the time from when they go
from um I'm just trying out this app to
I'm actually in a conversation with a
person that increases the aha moment.
And so sometimes that's a matter of
increasing friction because the friction
along the way gives you the information
or the motivation that you need and
sometimes it's a matter of decreasing
friction because you want to get a
person to a particular moment really
quickly. A framework I really like for
this is derise contractor has a
framework called the psych framework
where the idea behind it is that you can
psych a user up or you can psych a user
down as they're going through your
product and it's important to manage
that motivation in a really intentional
way and keep the motivation high.
>> Gotcha. Yeah. There's a um I pulled this
up and we'll put a link to this in the
show notes as well. There's a really
cool chart where it kind of tracks the
the psych where you add add five psych
points, add five psych points, and then
you hit an email form fill and that
takes away five psych points. You have
to enter your credit card, that takes
away 10 psych points. And thinking about
it in this way and kind of managing that
through the onboarding and you and
you'll probably you'll know the ones
that are creating this negative psych
because when you track in your
analytics, those are the ones people are
dropping off on. Those are the ones that
aren't performing as well. But you you
need to do some of those. But I like,
you know, you build up and then you cash
out and then you build up and you cash
out. And I like I really like the the
even the visual of it in that blog post.
Yeah, for sure. And like some people
don't think about this, but one of the
highest negative psych moments in a
typical onboarding flow is having to
define your password because you want to
you might have you be using a password
manager. You want it to be unique. You
want it to be secure. all of the stuff
that goes into that actually decreases
your motivation and maybe you bounce and
go back to scrolling on TikTok instead
of completing that form. And so so many
companies I think that have really good
onboarding flows have moved to just give
us your phone number and we'll send you
a onetime password and then you and then
you get in and if we need to set up a
password later we can do that or if you
want to log in with Apple or or Google
you can do that and that is like a
really good example of how taking out a
negative psych moment can just get a lot
more people through the onboarding
process and sometimes those
inefficiencies lie in places that you
think you have to do but you don't
necessarily have to do it. You said
somewhere that by creating this really
frictionless onboarding experience for
Tinder that actually expanded the TAM
for dating. What what do you mean by
that? How did you think about expanding
TAM through
more frictionless onboarding? The
problem that dating had at the time that
Tinder came out and this was I think
2012 time frame was that in order to get
into match or e-harmony, you had to fill
out 20 or even 100 questions, whatever
whatever it was, you need to spend 20,
30 minutes actually creating your
profile. And so only people who are
really serious about I think online
dating can work for me were actually
going to end up in an online dating
product. And so that meant that the
total addressable market for online
dating was pretty small. Instead, Tinder
massively decreased the friction to get
into an online dating app through a few
different things. One, by using Facebook
login, so you didn't need to create
account. Two, by having you just pick
pictures from Facebook that you wanted
to use for your profile. Three, by
having a short kind of Twitter-like bio.
And so you could go from kind of, oh,
maybe I'm interested in online dating to
actually swiping on people and maybe
talking to someone in less time that it
took to create your profile on
e-harmony. Massively less time. Instead
of 20 minutes, you could be in and
swiping on people in a minute and a
half, 2 minutes. And so that increased
the total addressable market because all
of these people who had very limited
willingness to pay with their time could
now actually get into a dating app for
the first time and see that it could
really work with them or work for them.
And so as a result, you had a lot of
younger people who had never considered
online dating before come into and use
the Tinder app. And that was a key
moment for online dating to go from a
niche market into, you know, a market
that nearly every single person in
America uses.
>> I love the dichotomy here where we we
and I I didn't intentionally play it
this way, but starting with increasing
to 25step checkout boosted conversion
40%. Everybody listening was probably
like, "Oh yeah, you know, I really
should add more onboarding. I really
should do more." But then Tinder doing
less is like what helped make it happen.
And I I there's probably a a happy
middle ground for a lot of companies
have a short one. I don't think there
the middle is the death zone because
like
>> Yeah. I mean, also, I don't know, buying
a GLP1, like that's a complicated, very
technical, very, you know, risks
associated and all this stuff. I wasn't
going to call Tinder a hookup app. Some
people may have called it that at some
point.
>> Maybe looking for hot people to go hang
out with, maybe date, who knows? Like,
that's a very, you know, everybody knows
how to do that, right? You know, there's
less less to explain there. You know
what I mean? It's like meet this person,
not meet this person, you know?
Attractive, not attractive, right? Like
to you like whatever. Like, stay away
from like the messy middle. You know
what I mean? Like know who you are. Like
are you the long onboarding or are you
the very very short onboarding and like
go hard on either, right?
>> I'll give another really interesting
example. And I think this all comes down
to motivation and confidence. Like you
want to keep person highly motivated
during the onboarding process and that
you want them to be confident that what
they're getting is what they want. At
Trip Adviser, we had tested out a new
algorithm. So it used to be that you
would always see hotels sorted by their
traveler ranking, so by their average
review score. Instead, we personalized
that based on your past behavior to show
you hotels that you were more likely to
convert on. We did some testing without
doing anything other than just changing
the algorithm. And we saw that people
were actually converting much better um
with the new just for you algorithm. And
then we rolled it out as just for you
and said, "Okay, now your default is
just for you. We've looked at your past
behavior. We're showing you a set of
hotels you're likely to convert on." And
as soon as we branded as just for you,
the conversion rate went went down. And
the reason that the conversion rate went
down when it was branded just for you
versus when it was sort of a blind
algorithm is that travelers don't want
you making decisions for them. They
looked at that at and said, you know,
Trip Adviser doesn't know what's just
for me. They don't know anything. And so
people converted less well. Even though
when we just did it for people and
didn't tell them, they converted better.
And so there's a combination of both
actually getting to the right answer for
the user, but also creating confidence
around that right answer. And that might
be a longer intake, that might be a
shorter intake.
>> If you're advising a startup and they're
like, you know, should we do a long
onboarding? Should we do a short? I
mean, ideally, you probably experiment
with both, but like what would be the
the thinking or framework to decide like
are we that short onboarding company or
are we that long onboarding? I would say
ask what is the aha moment and then what
do you need to do to foster the
confidence and the behavior to get a
person to that? the GLP-1 case, as Jacob
was mentioning, you know, that's an
injectable. This is the very first time
in most people's lives that they're
actually going to inject their
themselves with a medication. And so, it
takes a lot of information, a lot of
handholding for a person to even
consider whether or not they want to
talk to a doctor about it versus
something like dating, you know, short
profile, couple of photos. I just want
to get get in there. I want to see who
else is here, and I want to swipe on
people, match, and have conversations.
The consequence of the decision is very
different. And so as a result, the
intake should be optimized in a
different way.
>> Gotcha.
>> Same with travel, right? People travel
is a very high consequence decision.
People only do it once or twice a year.
They spend, you know, next to their car
in their house. That's the third most
expensive thing they do during the
course of a year. They want to make that
decision with the confidence that
they're making the right one, which is
not an algorithm telling them this is
the right thing for them, but is
actually them coming to the decision of,
oh, I looked at all of my options and
now I feel like this is the right thing
for me. Even if those two answers are
the same, they want to go through the
process of being confident about their
decision.
>> If you could draw some lines around what
your monetization is as well. And I I
think part of what's working for a lot
of apps with these long onboardings is
that there's you're showing the payw
wall in onboarding. And so you're not
necessarily getting them to that aha
moment before they see your payw wall.
And then especially if you're not a
premium product and have a hard payw
wall, you got to manage that psych to
getting them to the payw wall before
they really get to experience the
product. So you got to find a way to
like manufacture these aha moments, this
confidence, this excitement for the
product so that they get to that payw
wall at a state where they're willing to
start that free trial to then actually
get to experience the product. And so
for a premium product, maybe being able
to get to that that aha moment quicker
and then have the confidence that you're
going to monetize them in the long run
once they've had that experience uh is
is one way to think about it. And then
you could create value for people before
they've monetized. I think comm's a
really good example. As soon as you open
that app, you start to hear rain sounds,
right? And so their promise is we're
going to make you more calm. And they do
that before you've done anything on
intake. In fact, even their commercials
do that, right? They have those calm
commercials where they just did a timer
of 15 seconds of rain sounds. And so
they're delivering that the the value
that the product promises from the very
first touch point with the product. And
if you're doing that during the
onboarding, if you're creating value for
people, your onboarding could be as long
as you want. It could be 90 screens long
as long as you are creating the value
promise for the user that they want to
get from your app. And then you know at
that point they're ready, they're happy
to pay because they're like it's already
creating a lot for me. If on the other
hand your onboarding is it's like a IRS
form. It's like name, rank, serial
number, and you're just asking for
information. It's not even really clear
why you need the information. at some
point a person is going to get bored and
and bounce.
>> One of the things you talk a lot about
are frameworks and mental models. Why?
What's the value in frameworks and
mental models and how do you even define
those?
>> Yeah, I think the value is in we're
we're dealing with incredibly
complicated problems. We're trying to
build businesses. The tech industry is
moving really fast. Ultimately, products
live or die by user psychology. Whether
it's B toc or even B2B, right? there's
still a psychological element to it
about whether or not a person wants to
buy a particular product. And so we're
making decisions in a really intense and
fastmoving environment. I think
frameworks are helpful to be able to
say, let me take a step back from this
decision and start to think about it in
a simpler way and start to pull apart
some of the factors that might be
conflated and and come to a better
understanding of actually maybe if I
think about it this way versus that way,
you can start to think about well what
is the root cause that you're solving
for. Similar to what we've been talking
about, right? This idea of should you
have a short onboarding or a long
onboarding is a really key fundamental
question. And if you hadn't have been
thinking about in that way, you might
actually end up with a middlesized
onboarding and say, "Okay, you know,
balance of all the factors. I'm going to
do a little bit of this, a little bit of
that, and you know, end up with
something that's less opinionated and
less incisive because you didn't pull
apart the different things that were
conflated." And so I think the the magic
of frameworks is not that they do the
thinking for you, but that they help you
ask the right questions to pull apart
the factors that really matter.
>> Well, request for blog post. Um, if
you're uh have some free time, I I would
love to see a Ravi meta onboarding
framework of like how how to really
think through this these things that we
kind of loosely talked about, but have a
more framework approach to how to think
about onboarding. I think that would be
really fascinating. It's a really
interesting topic. I feel like
especially now with AI, you know,
onboarding is evolving very quickly.
Yeah, it's interesting to see what all
these different companies are doing.
>> Well, you you have a ton of different
frameworks and mental models that you've
published on your blog and talked about
on podcasts and you you put out prolific
in your content production. So, folks,
you can, you know, you can go to robbing
meta.com and follow them on LinkedIn and
stuff like that to to hear more. Um, so
I had like a a plethora of options to
draw from, but the the one I wanted to
talk through was NTS, narrative,
commitment, and tasks. So why did you
come up with that and and what is it?
Yeah, so it's an alternative to OKRs.
And the reason that we developed it was
we originally developed it at
TripAdviser and we were trying to get
really good at OKRs. We even um there
was a book at the time about OKRs. We
did like a mini book club. We all read
the book. We all started to talk about
it and what I saw then as well as what
I've seen with other companies is that
many companies want to get better at
goal setting. They have to get better at
goal setting. They try to adopt OKRs and
then it doesn't doesn't go well as they
had wanted and they spend, you know, one
quarter you try it out. You realize it
didn't go well. You make some changes
for the next quarter, make some changes
for the next quarter and then all of a
sudden, you know, a year has passed and
you haven't quite locked in your goal
setting framework and you've spurned a
lot of time trying to do that. And so
the question I was trying to ask is why
do people have such a hard time with
OKRs. And it comes down to I think
something very simple which is goals are
a three-legged stool. You need the what,
you need the why, you need the how. And
OKRs only have two of the legs. And
what's interesting is like this idea
that I got is from John Door's TED talk
on OKRs. He talks about goals being a
three-legged stool. And then he says
OKRs solve for two of the legs. And the
important thing that's missing from OKRs
is the third leg existed in a very clear
and direct way at companies like Intel
and Google because they were designed
around OKRs. And so OKRs could work in a
system where you had the strategic why
really well defined. But if you don't
have that strategy framework to go
alongside with OKRs, OKRs tend to break
down because they're incomplete. And so
the idea behind narratives, commitments
and tasks is that they are the three
legs of the stool and that they are
independent and so you can work with
just them without any other uh strategic
dependencies. Narrative is what is the
story strategically that we're trying to
solve with this set of work. Commitments
are the things that you are committing
to do to make progress on that story.
And tasks are the things that you'll
need to do in order to deliver on your
commitments. And so the narratives are
the why, the commitments are the what,
and the tasks are the how. And
collectively, those three pieces work
together to provide you with a set of
goals that can stand on its own, that
stand alone, that doesn't need to exist
within any other system. And so, as a
result, I found that people that have
have adopted them have found a really
good alternative to OKRs that, you know,
in some ways it's similar, but it works
better for people because it's got those
three parts.
>> How do you differentiate between a
commitment like and a task? uh just it's
just like accountability on completion
or
>> Yeah, it's a really good question. So,
one of the things with commitments is
that because OKRs use the term key
results. Most people think about key
results have to be a metric that we're
moving. Commitment is just something
that we say that we're going to do. It
could be moving a metric. It could be
completing a task. It could be launching
a particular program. It could be doing
some research. The commitments are the
set of things that we as a team believe
are necessary for us to make progress in
this area and they can be whatever you
want. If there's something that you need
to do during a quarter that is not
critical to making progress is not
something that you want to commit the
team to then it can be a task. But if
one of the tasks is so important that
you want the team to be 100% committed
to achieving that by the end of the
quarter then it should be a commitment.
And it can exist in both both areas.
Mhm. How do you uh I always find my my
biggest challenge with these systems is
uh people turning them into an
intellectual busy box, right? It's like
ooh something we get to word lawyer on,
right? Uh because and here's my here's
my thesis why it's like the work is
hard. Arguing about these frameworks is
easier, right, than the work. And so
people go people go this is my problem
and it's tractable. which is why like
David mentioned we tried OKRs and then
we kind of nuked them and then I've just
been like coming up with weird memorable
things every few quarters and I've kind
of adopted this like uh security through
obscurity uh in in corporate planning
which is like just changing things
periodically to keep people from getting
too used to any one model right because
I think it creates no matter what model
you use like the the org begins to kind
of like like a slime mold kind of like
grow around it right and kind of like
shaped like it
>> right which is not necessarily good,
right? So like um do you think this
system like in some ways helps evade
that or is it like an everpresent
problem at these frameworks?
>> I think there is a problem right just
around process and exactly what you're
saying which is you know people sort of
shape themselves around the system
they're working in. One thing that I
have found really effective is the word
commitment is kind of scary and so
people don't enjoy making commitments as
much as they do making goals or making
OKRs. It's like oh I got to I'm
committing to do this. I I take my word
very seriously and so people tend to
come up with fewer commitments and then
are really focused on them during the
quarter and actually
>> you the fact that people are talking
about commitments is a great forcing
function for conversation before you
actually say we're finalizing our NCTs
for this for this quarter. So I found
that that really helps. The narrative
helps because it's like okay let's spend
one or a couple sentences describing the
why. The commitments help because people
only want to commit to the fewest
possible things. Um, so it's usually
like three to five things and then the
tasks I think about is just a scratch
pad. Like it gives us a warm start on
the quarter. The goal is not to come up
with these lofty goals and then all of a
sudden it's day one of the quarter and
nobody's talked about how you're
actually going to implement any of
those.
>> Yeah. I love getting down to this
blocking and tackling level which we
don't always do on the podcast, but I
mean this is this is the messy work of
actually building great products is that
you need to think about these kind of
things. you know, if you just go right
to tasks and you don't have any kind of
narrative for why they matter, like what
are you even doing? But yeah, how do you
fit in all the like paper cuts and other
things, does that become a commitment
like we're going to, you know, knock
down the paper cuts this quarter and and
that's a a specific commitment or or do
you see those kind of paper cut tasks as
something that lives outside of this
framework? Yeah, I think that this goals
or NCTs or OKRs or whatever you call
them operate alongside with just an
overall culture around product and the
tenants that you have around what you're
creating. You if you have a tenant that
really values design or quality, that's
incredibly important and that should be
factored into the OKRs or the NCTs and
it should become a commitment if you
feel like you're moving away from that.
Right? If the product has gotten so
buggy that actually you have a bunch of
tasks on your goals for the quarter that
need to get done. They're not
necessarily like aligned to any
strategic narrative, but they just need
to get done because the product is
getting kind of crappy. It's like guess
what? That is your strategic narrative.
Your product quality is going downhill.
You're going to start losing users. Make
that the priority for the quarter is to
get your quality back to the bar that
you're setting for yourself. You know,
same thing with other things that feel
like maintenance. If it's gotten to the
point where it's no longer maintenance,
it's something that really needs to get
done, make that part of your strategy
because it's the it's that hygiene
around product that I think really
undermines companies where, you know,
they're so focused on what's next that
they don't actually build the thing that
the customer needs right now. I think a
really good example of this is Spotify.
I worked with Spotify product leader a
number of years ago and he said quality
is our most important feature. We ship
that first and then we get to everything
else. And I think that's a really good
way to think about things and that's
really like present in in Spotify. I
can't remember the last time like
Spotify cut out or crashed on me. Like
it never gets in the way of listening to
music. And that's very different than
some of the other things that they
compete against. And so if quality is
absolutely essential to you, make that
part of your strategic narrative.
>> How do you advise companies to think
through the narrative part? I mean, it's
actually something I've I've always
appreciated about Revenue Cat. And um I
know Jacob, you probably don't want to
take too much.
>> You need to advise a company to think
through narrative. It's like bof, good
luck.
>> It can be so clarifying. And so at
Revenue Cat, our mission is to help
developers make more money. And so much
of what we do, we talk about the culture
is to help developers make more money.
And it it just as an indie app developer
working on my apps, I've just never had
that kind of clarity of vision or
narrative around the products I'm
working on. Um so how do you think about
helping folks do that? Yeah. So I have
another framework um called the product
strategy stack which I really like to
use which says that product strategy is
actually five layers. It's company
mission is the top. Everything flows
from that. Then there's the company
strategy and then there's the product
strategy. Then there's the roadmap and
then there's the goals. And so actually
the goals are the output not the input.
And if you are saying our strategy is to
increase revenue by 10% next year um
let's look at what our roadmap should
be. I think you're in a world of hurt
because you actually have nothing that's
tethering you to what you should be
doing. Instead, if you're saying, you
know, our mission is to help app
developers make more money, then
everything flows from that and the goals
that you get out of that process will be
really aligned to the mission and that's
where you're going to get a strategic
advantage and that's where you're going
to be able to create something that's
really valuable for folks.
>> Jacob, how did you come up with that
mission? Did you go off on a on a
mushroom retreat for three days?
>> You know, I'm straight as an arrow,
David. Uh,
no. It was very near the beginning if
almost the beginning but what not the
exact beginning but like um it was
before we hired anybody but you know it
kind of fell out of you know in that
case the the the software a little bit
came before at least the phrasing but we
never would have worked on that software
if that mission wasn't important to us
to begin with right like we would have
picked a different thing to work on but
then I was very specific in making sure
it was pathy and rememberable you know
and and and you could put it on a
t-shirt and then uh just repeating it
day after day after day after day for
the last uh for the last eight years. Um
but like what I feel like software
really should just be an in or products
or companies in general should be the
like instantiation of a mission, right?
Who cares if a company exists, right?
Like that's sort of like a a legal
framework and sort of like a loose
agreement of co of cooperation. Um you
know the the narrative that's why I was
kind of joking is like the narrative and
the mission, you know, come first. I
suppose you can reccon a mission and a
narrative onto a a company and a product
or a company and a product that's lost
its mission maybe, but often I feel like
that flows from like founders and
founding team, right? But it would be my
hope that you know for Revenue Cat
specifically like we've ingrained the
mission so strongly like there's there
could be no concept of changing the
mission or changing the the narrative
because like that you wouldn't have a
company be a different company, right?
you know, you'd have to like split the
whole thing in two. Everything else
though is more fluid, right? Strategy,
product, roadmap, like all that stuff is
sort of, you know, so I think I I
Robbie, I think very much agree with the
stack. Like it makes a lot of sense just
like uh customer of one. We like do this
in so many words. We don't do
necessarily do it in a in a framework
sense, but like talk a lot about uh
everything else flowing from from
mission. But then at the bottom, you
said product goals. I guess that like
flows right into sort of tasks and
commitments, right? like what are we
trying to do on the product? Exactly.
Right.
>> Yeah. And that's the NCTS and the
strategy stack kind of go together to
create, you know, here's how we're
defining our strategy and here's how
we're going to execute against it.
>> And maybe that's a good exertation for
folks who are working on products that
aren't working.
>> Get your mission straight.
>> Is that Yeah. or or move on to a mission
that you're passionate and excited about
and like you know start over with
something that like has a narrative and
a mission first not just a product and
if your customer is not mentioned in
your mission that's a problem right I
think what's really powerful about the
revenue
>> I think that's a lot of people's mission
>> which you know a lot of companies
operate in that way and then it filters
through the entire organization and then
all of a sudden everyone's just like how
do we how do we just turn the screw on
our customers to get more money from
them And that is like the source of
disruption. Big companies get disrupted
because you know they start focusing on
themselves not their customers.
>> I mean it goes beyond companies. I think
if you look through like human
cooperation through history right like
the best and greatest empires and and
organizations were built not under the
guise of like extraction. It was all
under the guise of like you know a
righteous mission of some kind right of
some some belief system. Uh and then
they tend to fall when they become
bureaucratic morasses where everybody's
out for themselves, right?
>> We wouldn't know anything about that in
this.
>> No, you know, uh it's not like history's
littered with examples. But yeah, I
think it's exactly the same in
companies, right? And it's a delicate
balance. It's hard to maintain, right?
It's it's very lucky if it survives the
founders, right? I mean, you could even
look at Apple now and like you could ask
the question at least like did it
survive the founder in that case. I
think there's probably good arguments in
both directions, but it's TBD, right?
>> And it can seem like everything's fine
because the timelines are really long,
right? Like if you've done well by your
customer, you might have 10 years or 20
years or 30 years of products that you
can deliver that are extractive before
it catches catches up with you. But it's
important to like catch it before it
becomes a vicious cycle and that it's
impossible to unwind.
>> Yeah, I should do some I'm trying to
come off the top of my head of like
organizations that have lasted like a
hundred plus years postfounder, post
even founding family and stuff like
that. I don't know if you know any I
can't name them off top of my head. I'm
sure they exist though, right? Where
they're very like still very
missiondriven, still very
missionoriented even though it's been
like handed off many multiple times.
>> Microsoft is how old now? It's it's a
good example.
>> Okay. Yeah. Well,
>> I think it's 50 years old now, right?
>> We'll say they're on they're on
iteration three of leadership, right? Um
>> they're wandering through the wilderness
with
>> Balmer was Balmer was even kind of a
founder though, right? And like that
even goes to show how kind of touchy it
is, right? Um, and yeah, now with with
Satia, they might have somebody who's
like maybe potentially stronger than the
founder.
>> He's he's got that founder energy for
sure.
>> More adapted for the time, right? Like
he's he's a better founder for the
moment. Steve Blank has a really good
article about the visionary versus the
operator and how visionary CEOs surround
themselves with operators because they
need people to execute, but then they
when they focus on their succession,
they typically promote an operator into
their role. And the reason is because if
you had other visionaries around the
visionary to begin with, that would
cause conflicts. But companies need that
visionary. And so a lot of times you
have like Bill Gates was the visionary,
Bomber was the operator, and then you
had to have Satia come in and bring the
vision back.
>> Not to speculate too much about internal
Apple politics, but like there were a
bunch of folks that Steve had worked
with like Scott Forsttoall um and even
Johnny and Johnny and Scott didn't get
along. I I think those would all be
considered potentially visionary uh
replacements, right? So we ended up with
Tim obviously one of the greatest
operators in the history of business
>> uh but very clearly in the operator
bucket, right? And so yeah, that that's
that's a fascinating observation and
probably true. I'm gonna do some
research on organizations have survived
a hundred plus years and we think are
still very missionoriented because I I
think it's difficult it's difficult to
find.
>> Nintendo might be a good example.
>> That is a great example. Um and uh I
would recommend um the acquired podcast.
I'm going to offer another podcast, but
they did a really good multi-hour
breakdown on Nintendo. But like Nintendo
is also kind of a pseudo family company
in the sense that it's like passed from
like one generation to the next in in
sort of this like way that only Japanese
companies kind of can pull off. Arguably
more mission focused than they were at
the beginning.
>> Yeah.
>> Which is good. It's a good example.
Yeah.
>> So we're starting a new thing on the
podcast. I'm going to wrap each podcast
with three questions and I I prepped you
ahead because these are tough questions.
But what is the biggest fail of the year
in your mind? And and for operators,
this is going to be more directed at the
biggest fail in their business. Uh but
for you as a consultant, this could be,
you know, broader industry or, you know,
a client that you worked with. But
what's the biggest fail of 2025 for you?
>> I think the biggest fail is AGI. Like I
think everyone thought like this was the
year.
We have you to blame, Robbie, for the
for the black. Come on.
>> Yeah. I took some time off. I didn't
quite get to AGI fast enough. I think
this goes to a lot of what the tech
industry does bad is like either
overhyped things or underhyped things
and either it's like you know generative
AI is you can't do anything and it's
meaningless it's not that useful to um
we're all going to die and the truth is
somewhere in between it's been a magical
year in terms of agents and reasoning
models. Remember a year ago we didn't
have cursor
>> really
>> we didn't have cursor we didn't have
cloud skills we didn't have atlas or
comet we didn't have all the reasoning
models like all of this stuff has gone
incredibly well this year so it's
actually been a great year for Gen AI
and I think this whole idea that we're
in a bubble right now is coming out of
the fact that people thought we would be
hitting AGI this year and you know I
never thought that was the case I think
we're still a long way off that doesn't
mean that the things that are happening
right now aren't fundamental and
transformational
>> and so What's the biggest win of the
year?
>> Yeah, I think the biggest win of the
year is Claude. Like I used to use chat
GPT 90% of the time. And now between
Claude Code and the Cloud main app, I'm
using that almost 100% of the time. I
think they've done such a good job with
their models. They write well, the
reasoning is good. Their deep research
works well. Cloud code is pretty
exceptional in terms of how much it's
really lived up to an envision the
vision of an agentic coding tool. You
know, I think they've just done a great
job. They've focused on their core. or
they haven't gotten distracted by other
products um like Sora and and building a
browser and they've just gotten they've
focused on the essentials of what they
can do well and I've become really
dependent on it.
>> And the last question is growth would be
easier if
>> I think growth would be easier if
especially right now people focused
obsessively on turning their earned
audience into an owned audience. There's
all of these distribution channels right
now that are going through massive
shifts, whether it's SEO or the
algorithm changes on Tik Tok or YouTube
or LinkedIn or other places. Like it
used to be that if you got a pretty
sizable following, you could count on
that to distribute your products. I
don't think that's the case any longer.
Um, this is especially true for
YouTubers, for example. You know, now
what gets in front of users is really a
matter of the algorithm, not of your
following. And so I think it's very
important for companies to obsess about
how do I take an audience that I don't
own and turn it into an audience that I
do own. And I think that's the result of
three things. One is, you know, create a
direct channel with your audience,
whether it's email or something else.
And then two is create habits around
your content so people come to you. You
know, having a podcast that people are
coming to on a regular basis and
listening to is an extremely important
way to have people break through the
algorithm. And then the third and most
important thing is create habits around
your product. So, if you can create
those listening habits, if you can
create those usage habits, and you can
have a direct channel to your audience,
you'll be in a much better position to
weather what's happening, which is like
a pretty significant reshuffleling of
distribution.
>> Yeah, such a great answer. Well, as we
wrap up, anything else you wanted to
share?
>> Welcome people to follow me. I've got my
Substack. It's just blog.ravi.com.
You can also look me up at uh ravi.com.
I work with companies. So if you have a
startup or a company where you're
looking to figure out product strategy
or monetization, feel free to reach out.
We'd love to chat.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much,
Robbie. This was a ton of fun. Really
great conversation.
Went a lot of places I didn't expect.
Those are always
>> I told you I'm the bringer of podcast
chaos. Right.
>> Awesome. Thank you, Robbie.
>> Yeah. Thanks for having me.
>> Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.